Guide to the Harry Holtzman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harry Holtzman papers
1945-1987
GEN MSS 819
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
26.9
30 boxes
The Harry Holtzman Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs, negatives, slides, notes, personal papers, and motion picture films which document the life and career of author and educator Harry Holtzman, principally his work with and writings on the painter Piet Mondrian.
Holtzman, Harry, 1912-1987
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 28 (motion picture films): restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Elizabeth McManus Holtzman Irrevocable Trust, 1999.
Harry Holtzman (1912-1987)
Harry Holtzman was born in New York, and studied at the Art Students League under Hans Hoffman. In the early 1930s Holtzman traveled to Paris where he met the Dutch painter Piet Mondrian (1872-1944), and in 1940 sponsored Mondrian's immigration to the United States. From 1950 to 1975 Holtzman taught at Brooklyn College. He was the author and editor of several books on Mondrian and was executor of the painter's estate.
Arrangement
Organized into three groupings by date of accession: I. January 1999 Acquisition. II. March 1999 Acquisition, 1945-1987. III. June 1999 Acquisition.
Scope and Contents
The Harry Holtzman Papers contain correspondence, writings, photographs and negatives, slides, notes, personal papers, and motion picture films that document the life and career of author and educator Harry Holtzman, principally his work with and writings on the painter Piet Mondrian.
Artists; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Audiovisual materials; Color slides; Motion pictures (visual works); Negatives (photographic); Photograph albums -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Artists -- 20th Century; Holtzman, Harry, 1912-1987; Mondrian, Piet, 1872-1944
- January 1999 Acquisition, 1; 23.6; (25 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, photographs, slides, negatives, printed material, writings, including manuscripts and typescripts, notes, personal papers, and three 16mm films; the films are held in Box 28 as Restricted Fragile material.
  - Passports, datebooks, address books, certificates and awards, postcards, and art exhibit brochures, 25 (Box 1)
  - Notes and notebooks, 15 (Box 2)
  - Harry Holtzman photographs, 9 (Box 3)
  - Articles, notes and letters, 19 (Box 4)
  - European slides, 1980s; 6 (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, letters, file cards, personal addresses and phone numbers, 10 (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, letters, file cards, personal addresses and phone numbers, 9 (Box 7)
  - Book materials, lectures and correspondence, 16 (Box 8)
  - Arnold Newman, book photographs, Mondrian, Pollack, Duchamp, and Warhol files and postcards, 7 (Box 9)
  - Binder containing pages related to Piet Mondrian, DE STIJI., 1; Three ring binder (Box Box 9a)
  - Book notes and other papers, 35 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous files and correspondence, 36 (Box 11)
  - "Transformation" notes, articles, postcards, correspondence, and photographs of travels, 21 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous files including interview with Thelonius Monk, 29 (Box 13)
  - New Art New Life, early draft, 58 (Box 14)
  - Letters to and from publishers regarding Mondrian book, 19 (Box 15)
  - Contact sheets and strip negatives; photographs taken by Harry Holtzman, 14 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1985; 13 (Box 17)
  - New Art New Life: typescript, 19 (Box 18)
  - New Art New Life: typescript, 2 (Box 19)
  - New Art New Life: Mondrian articles, 29 (Box 20)
  - [Piet Mondrian] book drafts, 9 (Box 21)
  - General semantics, Mondrian book, 10 (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, personal addresses, cards, notes, articles, death certificate, and other papers, 80 (Box 23)
  - Oversize material removed from various boxes (Box 24)
  - PM notes binder, undated (Box 29)
    Holtzman's binder that formerly held material now in Piet Mondrian Papers (GEN MSS 1102).
- March 1999 Acquisition, 1945-1987; 2; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  - Condolence notes, 1987 (Box 25)
  - Beldrecht correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 25)
  - Tax records, 1980-1987 (Box 25)
  - Mondrian collection inventory, 1956, undated (Box 25)
  - Storage bills, 1982-1983 (Box 25)
  - Museum of Modern Art correspondence, 1945-1958 (Box 25)
  - Expenses, 1983 (Box 25)
  - Legal documents and correspondence, 1945-1983 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous notes and correspondence, 1956-1985 (Box 25)
  - Rolodex, undated (Box 26)
- June 1999 Acquisition, 3; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Personal notes; address book, undated; 6 (Box 27)
  - Collected writings, undated (Box 27)
  - Letter from Robert Motherwell, 1984 Mar 22 (Box 27)
- Restricted Fragile
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 28 (motion picture films): restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - 16mm films (3) (in January 1999 Acquisition), undated (Box 28)
    The three films are undated 16mm copies made at America Film Studios in Hamden, Connecticut. Film number 1 is labeled "Tiberius Palace '48." Film number 2 is labeled "man and woman on boat - lots of seagulls." Film number 3 is labeled "woman on hillside - horse - boats."